Of all the forms of fighting known to man,
one name strikes fear further into the
hearts of those who hear it.
Bare Knuckle.
For hundreds of years, the men of Britain
have rammed their unprotected fists into
each other's bodies to decide who was the
hardest of them all.
From noblemen, to travellers, to family
men and gangsters, being a bare knuckle
fighter is something that
marks you out from the rest of society.
It's a thoroughly British blood sport.
that gradually sank further into the
criminal underground as the rest of
society became more civilised.
It's a sport of legend, honour and
astonishing violence.
Bare Knuckle Fighting is a world that most
people think they understand, but few have
actually seen.
Now, a number of fighters and promoters
are trying to take it into the mainstream,
setting up the most anticipated Bare
Knuckle Fight in
over 150 years.
America versus Britain.
And I wanted to know if the sport can ever
truly take itself out of its underground
past.
The common perception of bare knuckle
fighting is that only Irish travellers and
East End hard men still do it.
But in actual fact...
they're still a thriving underground and
the fighters come from all walks of life.
And it originates here in the UK.
I'm here in Hinkley just outside Leicester
to meet Andy Topliff.
Now Andy runs a promotion company called
Be Bad Promotions and what he aims to do
with that company is to
kind of bring bare knuckle into the
mainstream.
It's an up and coming fight company and I
do it because I love the sport and I want
the sport to grow.
Intrigued to know more about the history
of bare knuckle, and why now it seems to
be on the up, we met at a patriotic pub
just outside Leicester.
Andy, how's it going?
Nice to meet you.
Hey, how are you?
What is the history of bare knuckle
fighting in England and Britain?
Bare knuckle fighting as a sport was
absolutely categorically English.
It was an English thing.
The Europeans feared Englishmen for their
fighting ability.
It's actually a British heritage, bare
knuckle fighting is.
It's where boxing comes from.
Certainly in the 18th century, very, very
big sport.
Even the royal family, they would want to
know who won, you know, if it was a big
fight.
They were like superstars of today.
And how about your own background?
How did you get into bare knuckle?
From a very young age, to be honest with
you.
You know, I was brought up in the
travelling community.
My hands, they're destroyed basically now.
They're deformed because of it.
Obviously in the bare knuckle world, there
has always been quite a lot of input with
criminals.
Do you know what I mean?
I wanted to push all of that out.
I wanted that gone.
You know, I decided to do B-Bad and keep
it as a proper sport.
I really want to get this regulated and
get it mainstream.
We started the first UK belt since, you
know, way over 100 years.
And then I thought, well, one extra step
and we'll go for the Atlantic belt, which
is a real historic event.
I'd always wanted to get, you know, an
American to come over.
Jason Young, this is the man.
who I've dreamt of getting over into this
country.
We're making history with this guy being
here.
The last time an American was in this
country fighting for a belt, you know,
against a UK champion,
1863.
It's a big deal.
Jason had flown into the UK prior to the
fight and had surrounded himself with some
of the most knowledgeable fighters in the
UK, including
ex-Bare Knuckle champion Paddy Monaghan,
famous for his friendship with Muhammad
Ali.
Three years it took us to get you here,
didn't it?
Three years, but I'm here.
No excuses.
No excuses, that's it.
I'm here.
And you're gonna prove the boys wrong,
innit, eh?
Oh yeah.
But he couldn't stick around for long, as
he was off to Wing Chun Grand Master
Samuel Kwok's martial arts retreat in
Blackpool, a man
who apparently once trained with Bruce
Lee.
Clearly, Jason was taking this fight very
seriously.
But whilst my own experiences of fighting
are fairly pathetic, I was intrigued to
meet a man who'd been fighting since the
age of 10, James .
Gypsy Boy McCrory from Newcastle.
A living legend in the bare knuckle scene.
and the man pitted up against Jason Young
in the Atlantic title fight.
We met him at his local haunt, a 50s
themed diner in the centre of town.
So what's good here?
Everything is good, but the burgers are
huge.
The reason why I come here is because we
were told to bring this here.
If we had just come here, they wouldn't
sell beer, you know what I mean?
So that's the truth.
Your nickname is Gypsy Boy.
Where does that come from?
Obviously I've travelled all over.
I've lived in Ireland and worked all over.
Is being Irish a big part of your fighting
heritage?
Yeah, I love Ireland.
I love going back there, I love seeing my
mum.
I love it.
I love spending time with my family,
honestly.
I love sitting in the city, like, cuddle,
watching TV, me.
Big softie.
Love my family.
You know, loads of people, they treat me,
get full of rides and all that crap, but I
prefer to get full of Guinness and full
of food, you know.
It's a much more fun way of doing it.
Yeah.
My days have been a model of well gone, so
don't worry about the old six pack
anymore, me.
You know what I'm saying?
You've got the cake.
That's it, I've got a full keg now.
James, a self-professed softie and family
man, invited us to his house to meet his
charming and long-suffering girlfriend,
Leanne.
I love being the life and soul of the
party, you know.
I'm Jack the lad, but then you don't know
where my bread's about, I don't know what
I mean, and I've got a good girl and she's
put up with a lot.
Hopefully one day I'll marry her late, you
know.
What does she do?
Drives me fucking bonkers, you know.
Howdy toots.
How are you doing lads?
Yeah.
Hey, how's it going?
How's life?
Do you want a cup of?
I'm alright, I'm fine.
Me and James are very, very different.
Like, you couldn't get two people more
different in regards to what we're like,
how we've lived our
lives, the choices we've made.
How do you feel about him being considered
a legend?
Erm, I find it funny.
Because it's James.
He gets fan mail now.
Which is quite funny.
The person you see on the fights on
YouTube, that's not him.
I know it is, but that's not the person I
know.
I don't like it, to be honest with you.
When you come back from the Dave Radcliffe
fight, his face was really bad.
There was blood on my pillow.
I cleaned them the next morning.
I thought there was some more blood on the
pillowcase.
I thought I washed the doorway twice.
There was blood on the pillowcase.
It was just awful.
It's not just about him having a fight,
it's the effect that it can have on us in
regards as a couple.
Build up to certain fights.
It's like a time bomb.
Last summer I had a bit of a bad time and
I thought, you know, this is not working.
I'm away.
But...
I've never seen anybody fight as much as
what he did to get me back.
Having learnt about the origins of Bare
Knuckle and spent time with some of the
biggest names in the game, it was time to
see it in the flesh.
B-Bab was holding an event in Colwyn Bay,
North Wales.
The first fight between a pair of
seemingly well-matched middleweights was
over in seconds.
The second and last fight of the night was
something that will stay with me forever.
Seth Jones, a 46 year old local solicitor
and lunatic known as the Bangor Hammer,
took on a man 20 years
younger than himself only to go the
distance in a fight that was as
controversial as it was thrilling.
The solicitor was bending the rules
somewhat.
Stop him when you know he's coming for
you.
Give up now, Stokes Come on Come on Come
on Come on Come on Come on Come on Come on
Come on Come on Come on Come on Come
on
Come on Come on Come on Come on Come on
Come on
It seemed odd to see so much blood in what
was supposedly a stalemate, but I couldn't
call a winner either.
Seth seemed like he'd taken more abuse,
but Aaron looked exhausted.
It was my first fight.
I put myself forwards for it when I saw it
on the internet for a 13 stone fighter.
How does it feel fighting someone who's 20
years older than you?
Don't really matter.
I've had street fights with older people
since I've been young, you know what I
mean?
I used to get in trouble fighting and all
that lot.
I think you're a more peaceful person.
Yeah, I'm peaceful anyway.
But you're also getting a lot of street
fights.
How does that kind of work out?
I used to get in street fights when I was
younger because I used to hang around with
the wrong crowd.
My genuineness was going a bit too much.
Now I know how it feels, I can control it
a little bit more, I think, in my next
fight.
I couldn't see out of my left eye.
I got poked in it.
I think it's a good result from both of
us.
I'm chuffed with it.
How do you feel right now?
Buzzing.
Do you think you'll feel worse tomorrow
morning?
You know what I mean?
I've had worse than this.
Yeah?
Yeah.
How does it feel fighting guys who are,
what, considerably younger than you?
Half my age.
Half your age?
That's just the nature of bare-knuckle
boxing.
I've fought guys older than myself.
I don't mind fighting younger guys.
I don't mind.
I just like fighting.
Do you fight in the streets?
No, no.
Them days, I used to have a lot of fights
when I was younger.
Built up a bit of a reputation in the
area, but it was a huge mistake in my
life.
Being a bit of a thug to being a bit of a
drug smuggler to going to prison.
And then I realised, you know, this is not
the life.
And so I decided to go back to school and
studied law.
In the time I'd spent in the world of bare
knuckle so far, I began to realise that
the sport had a kind of gravitational pull
for lost souls.
Many of the guys we'd spoken to seemed to
be people who'd made bad decisions in
life, and perhaps in bare knuckle they'd
found a way to
utilise their talents, which happened to
lay in a realm that normal society finds
barbaric.
However, I wondered if organised violence
was a cure or a symptom for angry young
men.
James Lambert
Hello friends, it's James, the author of
Be Happy in 24 Hours.
I used to be a very unhappy person, very
violent person, bare knuckle fighter,
bouncer and unlicensed boxer.
And these are some of the tips and
strategies that helped me change my life.
life and literally become the happy person
I am today, helping society and being the
happy coach.
Retiring from the sport undefeated, James
Lambert had taken a complete U-turn from
his life of violence and reinvented
himself
as a lifestyle and fitness coach, calling
himself Mr Happy.
How long have you lived here?
Quite a while, what has it been now?
I think it's coming up to two years.
We've basically moved here for the peace
and quiet.
And as you know, you can see it's a
cul-de-sac.
It's very peaceful.
We've got super neighbours.
Did you want one sugar, my friend?
So, were you always a fighter?
There was always this fascination with
fighting.
I was an unhappy, angry...
violent person.
I went out into the world and lo and
behold I found other angry, violent,
scared young men.
You know somebody would catch my eye, I
would catch theirs and a fight would
ensue.
It was that ridiculous.
Can you remember your first bare knuckle
fight?
Of course.
Mixed emotions even to this date because I
was terrified.
I used fear as a form of energy,
transmuted that into positive energy that
drove me into my
victories.
But again, I found it very empty.
When I got home, I was still left with my
problems.
Not just outside, but in my mind.
So the fight did nothing to make me happy.
And did you know other fighters who felt
similarly?
Well, you see, this is a thing that's
never spoken about.
Certainly not within that world where
emotion is immediately and very directly
equated with weakness.
A leopard can change its spots and that's
very important because I hear it a lot and
it's a mind virus and we accept things
because they're said.
They're not always true, we have to
examine this and so I want you, you may be
a parent and your son or daughter could be
going through difficulties
never give up on them, never give up on
them.
Your brother, your son, your friend could
be an alcoholic a drug addict, never give
up on them.
People have the power to change inherently
in them I've done it myself.
Even when you win, there was great pain in
my ribs could have been fractured or
broken, you know, always cuts to the
face.
But worse than that was the mental trauma.
It was realising again what I had done,
the person that I was becoming, and that
really did affect me mentally.
I think now looking back I became
depressed.
I suppose there were thoughts, thoughts of
self-harm maybe, thoughts of actually, you
know, if this is it, I
don't actually want to be, I don't want
any part of this.
And that was actually profoundly upsetting
for me and I felt terrible.
So that was actually a pretty low evening
and I'd like to say it
was the last but that did happen a lot.
James had removed everything that would
remind him of his past life as a violent
young man, apart from a punch bag which...
He still hangs in the garage where he
coaches his clients.
Do you still hit the bag?
Actually I've personally chosen not to.
I suppose it was about two years ago when
I decided to fully refrain from fighting.
And for me that's violence in word,
thought and deed.
So for me, at this current point in my
life, I'm open to change.
It might change next week.
Other people can keep it controlled.
I fear that the anger wouldn't just stay
here and again it would leak into other
aspects of my life.
So I've just made the personal decision to
not hit anything, if you like, for a
while.
And so far, I've been good to my word.
Meeting James is really surprising because
here you've got a guy who's in the bare
knuckle game for years and came out of it
undefeated,
yet in some way he feels kind of ashamed
and he will admit that he is haunted by
his past.
And looking at what he does now, it seems
that his entire life is this kind of
struggle to put that to bed.
And he does seem to be winning that
struggle, admirably so.
And the Mr.
Happy thing, I guess, is a way of him
keeping that down.
But behind that Mr.
Happy persona, you do see flashes of the
old James.
This kind of machine that used to render
men unconscious, as he said.
But he will be the first to admit that.
And he says that, you know, he hasn't
conquered his demons yet.
Now, in this kind of suburban life,
perhaps he's fighting his biggest battle
of all.
The first UK vs US bare knuckle fight in
over 150 years is just days away.
So we've come back to Newcastle to see
James McCrory, who's in the middle of his
training preparations.
Get in.
Weights down.
Like all my opponents, you've got to give
them a chance at the start, you know what
I mean?
So when you're coming out, are there any
kind of routines?
Newcastle means a lot to us and Ireland
does, and I'll be wearing my Newcastle top
and my Irish shorts.
Bastard.
Where would you like to see the sport go?
Maybe 10, 15 years time, you know.
It'll be hitting big arenas, you know,
but...
I'll be...
Well, maybe.
I might not.
If the money comes good, I'll look after
myself.
I might still be fighting in 15 years'
time.
Is that about the pressure, like?
Is that about the pressure, boys?
Thrive under pressure.
Whoo Shaz, man, quite...
Can you explain to me...
What it's like in the pit?
It's only like three bales are here, right
this way, three bales are here this way,
and you're taking two
steps into the centre, then you're there.
I'd be fainting with the jab or moving my
hand about.
If you can establish your jab, it's a good
thing.
Then obviously you get the one-two in, and
then obviously you're going to move your
head a bit, which I'd be trying to do if
someone was jabbing me.
Then maybe just come and do a bit, come up
to the centre, and bang, bring a body shot
in.
And honestly, I'd rather have it with me
with ten in the jaw than one good one
there, you know, because it really hurts.
How does it feel when you get one of those
there?
I can't even describe it, mate.
It's the worst feeling in the world when
you can't breathe and you've got a gum
shield in your mouth.
You try to spit the gum shield out but you
can't because you can't get your breath to
get the power out of your lungs to spit it
out.
You're going red, you're starting to see
little fucking stars.
Then you're going lower and lower and
lower to the ground.
It's horrible.
Eventually your hands will drop and then
boom.
Good night, you know what I mean?
And if I wanted to knock you out and I'm
looking for the chin about here, right?
You haven't brought your 14-pound hammer
here, mate.
So you're all fucking out of luck.
You mentioned being punch drunk earlier.
Do you think you could have a wake-up call
at all?
I've had some great nights with the boxing
and with Ben Otter.
If I wasn't so brain damaged, I could tell
you that Marley and I...
Do you worry it might affect your memories
of your family?
Those kind of important...
What moments
were heavy?
Well, probably already has, you know.
I mean, I can remember the day that my dad
died.
I can remember it all, every single second
of it.
But I can't remember much otherwise.
I could get hit by a bus, you know, and I
wouldn't have any memories at all.
So it's just a risk you've got to take,
isn't it?
That's why the tattoo's on my back, you
know.
McCrory is a Catholic cross, the shamrock
for my dad in Nerfia.
I'm going to be scared now in life, man.
You just go for it, whatever happens,
happens.
There's a lot more better fighters than
there's out there, but the difference,
I've got the balls to fucking...
I don't just talk about it.
If I say I'll turn for a fight, I'll turn
for a fight, doesn't matter where I go.
I don't think Leanne and my mother realise
just how big a part of this is in my life.
It's fucking great when you can take
someone's best digs and you can give them
your best and see who comes out better.
From spending time with James, what I
really began to understand was this idea
of heart.
I think a lot of us throw it out as like a
kind of...
Just a cliche, but actually looking at
James and the way he conducts his life
with this kind of very emotional attitude
towards the death of his father and his
relationship with his family and what he
does is he managed to channel that and
bring
it into the ring.
He breaks every cliche.
I mean he's not one of these guys who
comes around toting his unbeaten record.
He knows he's been beaten a few times and
he literally takes it on the chin and
accepts that And maybe he's the perfect
fighter
because he's fallible.
I love fighting.
I'm the American that's coming over here
across the Atlantic.
I mean, it's a big deal.
I don't think I'm going to lose.
That's not even in my mindset, you know,
it's not even an option to me.
You know, I've been a fighter my whole
life.
I feel like I'm the more skilled fighter.
I'm the bigger fighter.
I don't really give a damn what anybody
says because people are always going to
have opinions.
People are always going to doubt you.
None of that matters.
What matters is what happens in that pit
when it's me and him.
Me and James, I'm very ready to go.
It was the bare-knuckle extravaganza down
in South London.
The US vs UK Transatlantic Showdown.
The biggest bare-knuckle fight in recent
history.
Two champions, one from America, one from
the UK, fighting this
belt.
Two times since 1863 and this belt is
impossible.
But before the title fight, we were
treated to a few other terrors.
tear ups in the build up to the main
event.
It was a festival of physical abuse.
Blood, guts, glory.
I want to see people going for it.
Bare knuckle, it is the ultimate sport.
Yeah, ultimate tear up.
Just enjoy getting in there, you know,
real punches and no fucking around, you
know what I mean?
There's no old barbed wire left, you know.
They really go for it.
Violence and plenty of chances of getting
back at you.
Fucking good buzz, you know what I mean?
It's one of the best buzzes I've ever had,
you know what I mean?
It's up there with sex, my friend.
England is the home of bare knuckle.
I think the British, it's in the blood.
We're all day, man.
You know what I mean?
Fuck the fucking rest of the world.
Salt Lake City, Utah.
I'm here for Jason the Machine Gun Young,
USA.
Jason the Machine Gun Young, fighting for
the Atlanta Heavyweight title against the
UK champ James Justybill McCrory, and I'm
ready to kick his ass.
Jason was everything you'd expect an
American fighter to be.
Brash, verbose, and massively patriotic.
He'd even referred to himself as the bald
eagle on a few occasions.
Unfortunately today's bare-knuckle boxers
are mostly just boxers.
I bring a different style.
For me it's natural.
I tune everything else out, the crowd, the
noise, the cameras, everything, and just
focus on my opponent.
Just in the zone.
I'm the first American to come over here
since 1863 and fight for the title, so
there's much more pressure on him.
Because I'm the unknown, I'm coming for
the United States, we have a huge
advantage.
It was 10 o'clock, the scheduled time for
the fight, but James was still nowhere to
be seen.
Rumors that he was refusing to come down
was spreading throughout the crowd.
Some said he was in a cab on his way from
Newcastle, others said he bottled it.
This didn't sound like the James I knew,
but time was ticking on, and the success
of the night depended on his appearance.
Jason, who'd been in training for weeks,
had become increasingly agitated.
Well, I don't know what happened.
He got stuck up in Newcastle.
I mean, we've known about this fight for a
very long time.
I came all the way from America.
If I was back in America, I'd have a
hundred friends who would come get me
immediately and bring my ass down here.
So I basically just told them, you know,
get down here.
Seems like there's a lot of excuses with
today's fighters.
Back in the day, somebody called somebody
out and, you know, if you're going to be
disrespectful, you've got to back it up.
People were beginning to lose hope and
headed towards the exit.
It was looking likely that history
wouldn't be made tonight.
And suddenly, like the angel of the north,
he rose.
James McCrory.
A few stones heavier, a few inches to his
beard and wearing a Newcastle football
shirt had arrived.
Looking slightly bleary eyed, he'd fallen
asleep for the entire cab journey.
But was he too tired, too full of Guinness
to take on the machine gun?
After weeks of build up, training, mind
games and the threat of one of them not
even turning up, the Atlantic title fight
was about
to start.
We were here.
Here on the Edge of History, America
versus the UK, toe to toe, bare knuckle.
As the machine guns fist hammered down on
the struggling gypsy boy, it seemed that
the title might be heading across the
Atlantic.
But McCrory had other ideas.
Done it.
James McCrory have made sure that Britain
have won the bare knuckle bragging rights
and Young and his entourage were on their
way back to
Utah with their tails between their legs.
His victory marked a step into the big
time not just for Andy Topliffe's company
but for bare knuckle as a sport.
And perhaps it had moved closer to
everyone's dream of it becoming the
biggest, nastiest and most exciting blood
sport in the
UK.